Nicole: As we have already mentioned
the skills needed to be a cyber
security professional are a combination
of both hard and soft skills.
Diverse experiences of all areas
of a business can give that extra
help beyond the technical skills.
Understanding human psychology
can help when identifying issues
with social engineering threats.
Abraham: Project management and team
work along with marketing and PR
skills can also help a cyber security
professional working with a range of
different projects and departments.
Nicole: Let’s look at the range of skills
that are advantageous for those who wish
to work as cyber security professionals.
Cyber security is not just a
problem that affects one area
of a company or an organisation.
Most departments today rely on
digital communication and technology
and are therefore liable to be
vulnerable to a cyber breach.
Abraham: Cyber security professionals
will be called upon to resolve
issues across a range of areas making
good use of interpersonal skills.
Nicole: Interpersonal skills include a
variety of different skills including
the ability to listen to others and
respect their views and communicate
well both verbally and non-verbally.
They also involve working well and
collaborating with others whilst being
both self-aware and showing empathy.
Abraham: The ability to be able to
ask the right questions and give out
the relevant information are really
important in cyber security, as
are giving and receiving feedback.
Cyber security professionals have
to interact with staff at all levels
and educate others on the threats
an organisation may be open to.
Nicole: Critical thinking helps a cyber
security professional to be able to
be able to detect and troubleshoot any
problems or potential vulnerabilities.
It is the process of objective analysis
and evaluation of an issue to help with
decision making and includes using skills
of observation, experience and reflection.
Abraham: Attention to detail can
help a cyber security professional
with identifying potential
issues, whilst continuously
monitoring networks and systems.
Being able to defend an
organisation involves being highly
vigilant and detail oriented.
Nicole: A Strong Technical Knowledge Base
is one of the most obvious skill areas.
And it is not surprising that many cyber
security experts started out hacking!
It is important to know a system
fully to be able to understand
how it can be exploited.
Essentially a cyber security professional
needs to have the same skills as a
Hacker, but not the same inclinations.
Abraham: This can involve practical
hands-on techniques and more
conceptual technical knowledge.
Practical skills consist of the
ability to configure a network, conduct
a pen test or instal a firewall.
Nicole: Conceptual technical knowledge
involves everything from knowing how
to code and a variety of programming
languages to knowing how to subnet.
Abraham: Being able to code
using languages such as HTML and
JavaScript, can help to understand how
applications and websites are made and
therefore how they can be exploited.
Learning how to develop scripts
in languages like Python
can help to understand core
processes in potential roles.
Learning the intricacies of setting up
networks, LAN, WAN and VPN, can help gain
skills needed by many organisations and
businesses in their everyday operations.
Nicole: The ability to run, configure
and maintain common applications such as
databases and webservers are always in
demand as software and other applications
are integral tools for businesses.
Systems are key in cyber security,
so it is important to have a good
knowledge of desktop and mobile systems
including common operating systems.
Abraham: Cyber security as with all
technology is constantly changing and
cyber security professionals need to stay
at the top of the curve and therefore
must keep up to date with the latest
industry trends and best practices.
Nicole: Essentially a cyber
security professional needs to
have the same technical skills
or better, than a ‘Hacker’, to
be able to thwart their attacks.
Abraham: This often involves
educating themselves both during
working hours and in their own time.
It is a major commitment, but
it can also be very rewarding.